Guide to the Jazz Institute of Chicago Records 1959-2008
University of Chicago Library
Jazz Institute of Chicago. Records
1959-2008
10 linear feet (17 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
The Jazz Institute of Chicago is a non-profit organization founded in 1969 to help preserve the history of jazz in Chicago. The Jazz Institute of Chicago Records contain administrative material, publications, photographs, audio-visual material, articles, ephemera, and audio material which document the institution's events, board meetings, and involvement in the Chicago jazz community.
Information on Use
Access
Series IV, Musicians and Photographs, does not include access copies for part or all of the audio material in this series. Researchers will need to consult with staff before requesting material from this series.
The remainder of the collection is open for research.
Historical Note
The Jazz Institute of Chicago (JIC) was founded in 1969 by members of the jazz community to help preserve the history of jazz in Chicago. Founding members include Art Hodes, Muhal Richard Abrams, Harriett Choice, Joe Segal, Bob Koester, Don DeMicheal, Penny Tyler, and John Steiner. As part of the effort to preserve the history of Chicago jazz, the Jazz Institute of Chicago helped found the Chicago Jazz Archive, located at the University of Chicago.
The Jazz Institute of Chicago created numerous ongoing events and festivals, including the Annual Jazz Fair, Chicago Jazz Festival, and Jazz Club Tour, as well as many individual concerts and performances. In 1997, the Jazz Institute of Chicago partnered with the Chicago Park District to promote the JazzCity concert series and also partnered with the American Composers Forum in 1999 to create the Chicago Composers Project.
Though the original focus of the Jazz Institute of Chicago was to preserve the history of jazz in Chicago, over time the scope has broadened to not only preserve that history but to also bring jazz and other types of music to new audiences. One program is Jazz Links, a forum for young musicians to play. The Jazz Institute of Chicago also works with the Chicago public schools and other organizations for educational programming.
Scope Note
The Jazz Institute of Chicago Records is organized into five series: Series I, Administrative; Series II, Events; Series III, Publications; Series IV, Musicians and Photographs; and Series V, Oversize. The Jazz Institute of Chicago Records contains administrative material, publications, articles, ephemera, and audio material, which document the institution's events, board meetings, and involvement in the Chicago jazz community.
Series I, Administrative, contains meeting minutes, agendas, budgets, and correspondence from board of directors and committee meetings. There are copies of the by-laws as well as grant information and applications, news releases, brochures, and documentation about website development. Also included are correspondence and other documents with and/or about other jazz related institutions.
Series II, Events, contains a guestbook, articles, fliers, brochures, posters, invitations, postcards, buttons, and other ephemera about Jazz Institute of Chicago sponsored events, performances, conferences, and festivals. Material about the Chicago Jazz Festival include correspondence, press kits, release forms, budgets, articles, reviews, fliers, buttons, and programs. Articles are mostly obituaries of musicians as well as announcements and reviews of performances, exhibits, and other events. See Series V, Oversize, for additional event material.
Series III, Publications, contains newsletters and magazines from jazz societies, organizations, and Chicago jazz publications.
Series IV, Musicians and Photographs, contains articles, photographs, press kits, audio cassettes, and a compact disc of musicians, primarily for auditions of the 1986 and 1987 Chicago Jazz Festivals. There are also photographs and slides of Jazz Institute of Chicago sponsored events. See Series V, Oversize, for additional photographs.
Series V, Oversize, contains posters and ephemera about jazz events in Chicago, and a copy of "Jazz at the Philharmonic" by Norman Granz. Also included are photographs of Tommy Bridges, Billy Brimfield, Doc Cheatham, John DeFauw, Franz Jackson, Steve Jenson, Billy Perry, Bill Rank, Paul Serrano, Joel Spencer, and Mr. Wonderful.
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
Bob Koester. Collection
Charles Bryant Frederick Weeks. Collection
Don DeMicheal. Papers
Harriett Choice. Collection
Jamil Figi. Papers
John Steiner. Collection
Subject Headings
Jazz Institute of Chicago; Jazz; Jazz -- Illinois -- Chicago; Jazz -- Periodicals; Jazz festivals; Jazz musicians; University of Chicago. Chicago Jazz Archive
INVENTORY
- Series I: Administrative
  - Archives Committee, 1986-1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Board of Directors, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Board of Directors, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Board of Directors, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Board of Directors, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Board of Directors, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Board of Directors, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Board of Directors, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Board of Directors, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Board of Directors, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Board of Directors, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Board of Directors, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Board of Directors, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Board of Directors, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Board of Directors, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Board of Directors, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Board of Directors, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Board of Directors, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Brochures, 2000-2002 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - By-Laws, 1986-2000 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival Committee, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival Committee, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1991 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Education Committee, 1987-1989 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Friends of Downtown, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Fundraising, 1997-2000 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Fundraising Committee, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Grants, Doris Duke Charitable Foundation, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Grants, National Endowment for the Arts, 1986-2000 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Grants, National Endowment for the Humanities, 1982-1988 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Grants, National Endowment for the Humanities, 1982-1988 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Jazz Alliance International, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Media Committee, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Membership Committee, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Memberships, 1987-2003 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - The National Jazz Museum, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - News Releases, 1980-1996 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Nominating Committee, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Oral History Interviews, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Programming and Events, 1985-2001 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Public Relations Committee, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Stationery, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Website, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Series II: Events
  - African American Military Museum, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Articles, 1986-2003 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Arts Midwest, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Blackstone Hotel, 1979-1994 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Buttons, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Chamber Music Chicago, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Chicago Composers Project, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Chicago Edge Concert Series, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Chicago Historical Society, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 2001 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 2001 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 2003 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 2003 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, 2008 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Chicago Jazz Festival, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Chicago Public Schools, 1986-1987 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - DuSable Museum of African-American History, 1997-2003 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - The Field Museum, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - First Chicago Center Theatre, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - The Great Lakes Experience, 2003 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Guestbook, 1987-1996 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Henry Threadgill's Very Very Circus, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Hothouse, undated (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Humboldt Park, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Jazz Club Tour, 1993-1994 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Jazz Club Tour, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Jazz Club Tour, 1996 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Jazz Club Tour, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Jazz Club Tour, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Jazz Club Tour, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Jazz Club Tour, 2003 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - The Jazz Express, 1988-1989 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Jazz Fair, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Jazz Fair, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Jazz Fair, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Jazz Fair, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Jazz Fair, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Jazz Fair, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Jazz Fair, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Jazz Fair, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Jazz Fair, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Jazz Fair, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Jazz Fair, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Jazz Fair, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Jazz Fair, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Jazz Fair, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Jazz Fair, 1999 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Jazz Fair, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Jazz Fair, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Jazz Fair, 2002 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Jazz Fair, 2003 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Jazz Fair, 2004 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Jazz in the Public Schools, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - The Jazz Showcase, 1989-2000 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Jazz Unites, 1997-2000 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - JazzCity, 1998 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - JazzCity, 1999 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - JazzCity, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - JazzCity, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - JazzCity, 2002 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - JazzCity, 2003 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - JazzCity, 2004 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Limelight, undated (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - The Mayor's Office of Special Events, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Museum of Contemporary Art, 1996-2003 (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Museum of Science and Industry, 1999 (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Music Everywhere, 2002 (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - New Regal Theater, undated (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - North Park Hotel, undated (Box 8, Folder 33)
  - Now's the Time, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 34)
  - Palace Theater, 1996 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Playboy Jazz Festival, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Playin' Ta Win, 1999 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Rick's Café Americain, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Rock'n Chicago, undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Round Midnight, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Southend Musicworks, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - University of Chicago, 2004 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - University of Illinois, Chicago, 1979-1989 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - World Music Festival, 2000 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Non-Chicago, 1992 (Box 9, Folder 11)
- Series III: Publications
  - The Jazz Sheet, 1969-1978 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Jazzgram, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Jazzgram, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Jazzgram, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Jazzgram, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Jazzgram, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Jazzgram, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Jazzgram, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Jazzgram, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Jazzgram, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Jazzgram, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Jazzgram, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Jazzgram, 1992 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Jazzgram, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Jazzgram, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Jazzgram, 1995 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Jazzgram, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Jazzgram, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Jazzgram, 1998 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Jazzgram, 1999 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Jazzgram, 2000 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Jazzgram, 2001 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Jazzgram, 2002 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Jazzgram, 2003 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Jazzgram, 2004 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Jazzgram, 2005 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Jazzgram, 2006 (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Series IV: Musicians and Photographs
  - Bennett, Don, Quartet, Cassette, 1987 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Cables, George, 1987 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Cal Collins/Jimmy McGary/Steve Schmidt/John Von Ohlen's Blue Wisp Big Band, Cassette, undated (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Carvin, Michael, 1988-1989 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Clayton, Jay, Cassette, undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Cole, Freddie, Cassette, 1985 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Cooper, Jerome, 1983-1986 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Cullum, Jim, Jazz Band, Cassette, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Dallwitz, Dave, Jazz Band in Chicago, Cassette, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Davis, Wayman, Cassette, 1986 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - DeFauw, John, 1984 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Goode, Brad, Quintet, Cassette, 1986 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Harris-Dekker, Caroline, Cassette, 1987 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Horiuchi, Glenn, Cassette, 1988 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Kendrick, Matt, Unit, Compact Disc, 1991 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Kent, Willie, undated (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Kuhn, Steve, 1986-1987 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Maia, undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - McDougal, E. Parker, undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Out of Indianapolis, Cassette, 1988 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Pallato, Joanie, Cassette, 1986 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Redman, Dewey, 1985-1986 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Reese, C. Wardell, Cassette, 1986 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Santez Quartet, Cassette, undated (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Stephens, Lester, and Modern Traditional Jazz Band, Cassette, 1987 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Stidham, Arbee, undated (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Torff, Brian, 1987 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Vig, Tommy, Cassette, 1985 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Vignola, Frank, Hot Club Quintette, Cassette, 1988 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Walls, Laura E., 1987 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Walrath, Jack, 1987 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Walton, Charles, 2003 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - WASO Quartet, 1990 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Wheeler, Clarence, Cassette, 1986 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Zeitlin, Denny, and David Friesen, undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Photographs, Art Ensemble of Chicago by Joseph Banks and Angela Lee, undated (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Photographs, Board Meeting, 2000 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Photographs, Chicago Jazz Festival, 1990 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, A Mini Jazz Festival at Limelight, undated (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Photographs, Soundstage with Music of John Hammond, 1975 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Slides, Chicago Jazz Festival, 1979 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Slides, Chicago Jazz Festival, 1979 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Slides, Chicago Jazz Festival, 1980 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Slides, Chicago Jazz Festival, 1980 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Slides, Chicago Jazz Festival, 1980 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Slides, Chicago Jazz Festival, 1980 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Slides, Chicago Jazz Festival, 1980 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Slides, Chicago Jazz Festival, 1980 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Slides, Chicago Jazz Festival, 1980 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Slides, Chicago Jazz Festival, 1980 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Slides, Chicago Jazz Festival, undated (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Slides, Chicago Jazz Festival, List of Performers, 1979-1983 (Box 16, Folder 12)
- Series V: Oversize
  - Chicago Tribune Magazine, 2001 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Events, Chicago Jazz Festival, 1979 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Events, Chicago Jazz Festival, 1989 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Events, DuSable Museum of African American History, 1995 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Events, Round Midnight, 1986 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - "Jazz at the Philharmonic" by Norman Granz, undated (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Photographs by Boldt, undated (Box 17, Folder 7)